The escape from the Yanome prison
（観察者）ヤノメの監獄からの脱走
brought about an unexpected situation.
それは予想外の事態を引き起こした
March's death.
マーチの死
It was the second human death
that Fushi had witnessed,
それはフシが直面した
２度目の人間の死であり
and it became a source of new stimulation.
新たな刺激の獲得でもあった
Through its encounter
with this mother, March,
マーチという母親との出会いにより
Fushi became ever so
slightly more human-like.
わずかな人間らしさを得たフシは
Left with only her lingering
scent, it set off.
彼女の残り香を追って
歩き出したのである
♪～
～♪
（ニオイを嗅ぐ音）
Fushi walked, seeking more stimulation.
（観察者）フシは次の刺激を求め
歩き続けていた
It spent most of its time in the wolf's form.
大体の時間は
オオカミの姿で過ごした
This helped it choose its
next destination by smell.
ニオイで 次に進む方向を
決めるためである
It didn't take the bear's form.
クマにはならなかった
In that form, it felt unrelenting pain.
体が絶え間なく痛いからである
At times, it took the boy's form,
たまに少年になった
but there was little reason to.
ほぼ意味はない
When it became hungry,
it would take on March's form.
おなかが空くとマーチの姿になった
That way, it could climb
the fruit trees with ease.
この姿になると
うまく果実のなる木に
登れたのである
（フシ）ん？
And then, it came across a familiar scent.
（観察者）そして…
知っているニオイに たどり着いた
Our Goals
（茂みが揺れる音）
（ピオラン）ハッ
You're alive?!
お… お前 生きとったんか！
You have no idea what I've been through!
こっちは大変だったんじゃ！
I was lost for three days and nights,
３日３晩 わし１人で道に迷って
I had to ask villagers for food to stay alive,
民家でメシ恵んでもらって
食いしのいで
I tried to give the donkeys water
and they ran away on me,
ロバに水飲まそうとしたら
逃げられて
and I spent all this time here,
hiding from the rain and wind!
ずっと ここで雨風しのいで…
あっ
That girl... Parona, was it?
She's not with you?
あのパロナとかいう娘は
一緒じゃないのか？
And that monster, Fushi.
それと あのフシとかいう魔物
Hey, say something!
こら 何とか言わんか
（変身する音）
Oh, it was you?
ハッ
何じゃ お前だったのか
No wonder you're so quiet.
どうりで無口なわけじゃ
あ…
Either way, you're the only other one here.
とにかく今は お前しか
おらんちゅうわけか
Where are you going?
え？　どこへ行く？
Hey!
おおい…
年寄りを１人にしたら いかん！
Don't leave an elder all by herself!
I don't have the slightest
sense of what you're thinking.
（ピオラン）お前は何を
考えとるのか全く分からんな
What goes through your head
when you take on March's form?
どんな気分で
マーチの姿になるんじゃ？
Do monsters have feelings
or think about things?
魔物でも
ちょっとは感情があったり
考え事をしたりするのか？
I can see that if you do, you don't
have the means to express any of it.
それを表現する方法を
持っとらんのは
見りゃ分かる
ハァハァ… ハァ…
I'd like to get a look
inside your mind one day.
いつか お前の心ちゅうものを
のぞいてみたいね
（おなかが鳴る音）
I'm so hungry...
腹が空いた…
I haven't had anything to eat in two days.
おとといから何も食べてない
Hey, let's take a break.
なあ そろそろ休まんか？
Water...
水…
Meat...
肉…
はああ…
（ピオランの荒い息）
Thigh meat!
もも肉！
（フシ）ハッ
（ピオラン）うわ… ぐっ
（フシのうなり声）
It's not like you'll lose anything!
減るもんじゃなかろうが！
Let me cook it!
焼いて食わせろ！
Be good to your elders!
お年寄りを大切にしろ こら！
Get over here!
逃げるな！
（苦しそうな息）
あ…
あああ… 鬼！
You monster!
ハッ
I'm begging you! Give me some!
ううう… お願いじゃ
わしにもくれ！
I can't go on any longer!
もう かまんから！
うっ イテ…
おっ おおお…
Yum.
ウマい…
あ…
ウマい！
Yum. Yum.
ウマい ウマい…
ああ ウマい…
ウマい！　う… ウマい
ウマい ウマい…
（ピオランがかぶりつく音）
"Thank you"?
あ り が と オ！
Thank you, thank you.
ありがとう ありがとう
いい子じゃの
What a good girl.
（足音）
It's a map.
（ピオラン）おお 地図じゃ
What's this?
なんと！　町があるな
There's a town!
Though it's 100 ri away.
といっても100里も先じゃが…
We could also walk toward the sea.
このまま海に出るのも ありじゃな
What do you think, Fushi?
どうじゃ フシ？
My hometown is beyond the sea.
海の向こうに
わしの故郷があるんじゃが
Shall we go?
行ってみんか？
ん？
What...
何じゃ？
おお…
（フシ）んー… んー…
Are you interested in writing?
お前 文字に興味があるのか？
ハッ
Look. This is how you write "ri."
（ピオラン）ええか “り”は
こう書くんじゃ
（フシの鼻息）
That's it.
そうじゃ
（フシの鼻息）
（荒い鼻息）
Want to learn more?
（フシ）あ…
（ピオラン）もっと知りたいか？
Then come with me.
ならば わしに ついてこい
I'll teach you all about words and
writing and living as a human being.
言葉 文字
人間としての生き方を
わしが教えてやろう
And you take better care of me.
そして もっと わしをいたわれ
（フシの荒い鼻息）
This says "March."
（ピオラン）
これは“マーチ”と読む
（フシの鼻息）
No, not like that.
（ピオラン）
そうじゃない こうじゃ
Like this.
This says "Fushi."
これは“フシ” お前のことじゃ
That's you.
"Parona."
“パロナ”
This is my name.
これは わしの名前
"Pioran."
“ピオラン”じゃ
That's a "tree."
あれは“木”
Those are "flowers."
あれは“花”
Bird.
“鳥”
Sun.
“太陽”
Yum!
ああ ウマい！
（フシ）あああ…
River.
“川”
（フシ）かワ
（ピオラン）うむ
Fish.
（ピオラン）“魚” “火”
Fire.
Fish.
（フシ）サかナ
Fire.
（フシ）ヒ…
（ピオラン）うむ
Thank you.
ありがとオ ありがとオ
That's not wrong, but there's a
better word for this situation.
間違っちゃいないが
もっと適した言葉がある
"Yum"!
ウマい！
Yuf!
（フシ）うまイ！
（ピオラン）うむ
Yum.
うまイ うまイ…
Goodnight.
（ピオラン）おやすみ！
（フシ）おやすミ
What's that?
あれ ナニ？
That's a boat.
（ピオラン）船じゃ
Fish.
（フシ）さかな
（ピオラン）うむ
Fruit.
（フシ）クダモノ
（ピオラン）そうじゃな
Yup.
You sure have learned how
to say lots of things, huh?
（ピオラン）それにしても お前
たくさん しゃべれるように
なったの
I have.
（フシ）なった
Do you think that's thanks to March?
その変化はマーチのおかげかの？
To grow up is to learn.
大人になる
知ること
Oh?
何だ
You want to become a grown-up?
お前 大人になりたいのか？
Say, where were you before you met March?
なあ
お前はマーチと出会う前
どこで何をしていた？
What did you do? Who were you with?
誰といた？
I walked all by myself.
（フシ）ずっと歩いた １人で
Then I met him.
そしたら 会った
He gave me food.
ゴハン… くれた
Who?
（ピオラン）誰じゃ？
誰に会ったんじゃ？
Who did you meet?
I don't know.
（フシ）分からない
I don't know his name.
名前 知らない
Shapes, sounds, smells... I remember.
形 音 ニオイ 覚えてる
I became that person.
ボク その人になった
The end.
終わり
（ピオラン）
おっ 陸が見えてきたぞ！
We're coming up on land!
See how the sky is red over there?
あそこだけ空が赤いじゃろ
The Yanome fight like that every day.
ヤノメは毎日ああやって戦っとる
With Takunaha, where we're about to go now.
これから行くタクナハとな
My lover's home is that way.
（ピオラン）
この先に わしの恋人の家がある
We'll go there first.
とりあえず そこに行くが
Let's rest in this forest for the night.
今晩は この森で休もう
He's an intellectual.
ヤツは知識人でな
He might know something about you.
お前のことも
何か分かるかもしれん
We'll be there by the end of tomorrow.
明日には着くじゃろう
What's this?
（観察者）おっと…
It seems someone's come
to play in my garden.
私の庭に誰かが遊びに来たようだ
ハッ
（フシのうめき声）
Its flesh responds differently than usual.
（観察者）
肉体の反応が いつもと違う
It tries to take on the form
of the boy, but to no avail.
少年の姿に戻ろうとするが
ままならない
ん？
What is it, Fushi?
どうした フシ？
何かあったんか？
Is something the matter?
あ…
（風の音）
（フシのうなり声）
（うなり声）
Wh-What are you?!
な… 何じゃ お前は！
Why do you look like Fushi?
フシみたいな顔しおって
What do you want from us?!
わしらに一体 何の用じゃ…
Though your flesh may be immobile,
surely you can hear my voice.
（観察者）肉は動かずとも
声は聞こえるだろう
Well?
どうだ 自分の一部を
失った気分は？
How does it feel to have
lost part of yourself?
It took a piece of you.
お前はヤツに奪われた
That boy.
あの少年を 形を 音を ニオイを
His shape. His sound. His scent.
As it stands, you can't recall what
it was that it took from you.
このままでは お前は
何を奪われたか思い出せないだろう
But you must have noticed that
emptiness, that discomfort.
しかし気づくはずだ
その空洞に 違和感に
Is that over there of value to you?
あそこにあるのは価値あるものか
I'll give you some advice that's
suited for your intellect.
お前の知能に合わせて
助言をしてやろう
That is your enemy.
あれは お前の敵だ
Fight it, and win.
あれと戦って 勝て
（フシの吠(ほ)え声）
（吠え声）
（うなり声）
There's a core in its midsection.
（観察者）中心部に核がある
Rip that core out of its flesh.
そいつを肉から引きちぎれ
That will stop it from moving.
そうすれば動きは止まる
（フシの鳴き声）
Not bad.
（観察者）悪くない
（ピオランの荒い息）
Fushi!
Don't come.
フシ！
（フシ）こっチ だメ…
（ピオラン）ああ！
That steals the vessels
that you've collected.
（観察者）
あれは お前が集めた器を奪い
It's designed with the
objective of weakening you.
お前を弱体化させることを
目的に設計されている
（フシのうなり声）
It's a failure of life,
incapable of becoming an animal.
動物になれない生きそこないだ
（フシの雄たけび）
But it's adept at stealing.
（観察者）しかし奪い取るのには
特化している
（オオカミの吠え声）
（フシの叫び声）
（フシのうめき声）
（叫び声）
（雄たけび）
（フシのうなり声）
Well done.
（観察者）よくやった
That's the core.
あれが核だ
Inside it is everything it stole from you.
あの中に
お前が奪われたものがある
（クマの雄たけび）
All that's left is to take it back.
（観察者）あとは取り返すだけだ
（フシ）んっ！
（クマのうなり声）
（フシの力み声）
（フシ）うう…
う… ううっ
あっ
ああ… んっ
（フシ）くっ
（フシの荒い息）
（フシ）フゥ
んん…
んっ
あ…
ああ…
あっ
フゥ
What are you?
ナニ… お前？
I am your maker.
（観察者）私が お前をつくった
We have a grand objective.
私たちには大いなる目的がある
To preserve this world.
この世界を保存することだ
And this entity was sent to this
world to impede our objective.
そして こいつは
その計画を阻むために
放り込まれた存在だ
It seems you don't understand.
ピンときていないようだな
That's fine.
問題はない また話しに来る
I'll come to speak with you again.
Well, Fushi, we shall have fun.
ではフシ 楽しくやろう
Until the coming end.
（観察者）
きたる終わりの そのときまで
Hey!
（ピオラン）
おい！　大丈夫か フシ？
Are you all right, Fushi?
What was that thing?
さっきのは何だったんじゃ！
Fushi?
フシ？
（フシ）ハハ…
I don't know.
分かんない ヘンなの
That was weird.
Hey! Where's the old man?!
おい！　ジジイおるか？
Be grateful! Pioran here
has brought a gift for you!
このピオランが お前のために
土産を持ってきてやったぞ
An immortal freak!
不死身の怪物じゃ
♪～
～♪
Preview
Fushi and Pioran begin a new
life at the old brewer's home.
（観察者）酒屋の老人の家で
フシたちの新しい暮らしが始まる
The masked boy, Gugu,
welcomes Fushi with cheer.
フシを明るく受け入れる
仮面の少年グーグー
And Fushi's presence brings
about change in Gugu himself.
そしてフシの存在は
グーグー自身にも
変化を起こしていく
The Boy Who Wants to Change